Guide to the David Park Correspondence with Howard and Dorothy Baker, 1937-1952
Department of Special Collections
David Park correspondence with Howard and Dorothy Baker,
1937-1952
Misc 0962
Park, David, 1911-1960
3 folders
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The friendship of Howard and Dorothy Baker, Mildred and Bertrand Bronson and Lydia and David Park was intimate, stimulating and youthful. Baker was Yvor Winter's protégé, and a genius. Dorothy was writing or had just published YOUNG MAN WITH A HORN, and had begun to reveal her lesbian inclinations. Bertrand Bronson was a Rhodes scholar and the finest English Litetature intelligence ever at Berkeley. All were Young at this time, and all recombined for a period in Cambridge (early on).
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2001.
Biography
Born in Boston, Mass., David Park studied at The Otis Art Institute in Los Angeles in 1928. Upon moving to the San Francisco Bay area, Park first taught at the California School of Fine Arts, 1944-52, and then at the University of California at Berkeley from 1955-60. A figure painter in the 1930s and `40s, Park began experimenting with Abstract Expressionism in the 1950s, greatly influenced by the works of Clifford Still and Mark Rothko. Park then reconsidered his earlier interest in the human form, now through an Expressionist eye, and became one of the foremost proponents of the New Figurative movement in the Bay Area. He died of cancer in 1960.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Includes letters from both David and Lydia (Deedie) Park, and recipients include Bertrand and Mildred Bronson in addition to the Bakers.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Baker, Dorothy, 1907-1968.; Baker, Howard, 1905-; Bronson, Bertrand.; Bronson, Mildred.; Park, David, 1911-1960.; Park, Lydia (Deedie); American literature--20th century.; Art, Modern--United States.
Collection Contents
- Series 1: Park (David) & Park (Lydia) correspondence with Howard Baker and Dorothy Baker (his wife)
- ALS to Howard Baker, 3 pp, 1937 (Folder 1)
- TLS to Howard Baker, 2pp, undated (Folder 1)
- TLS to Howard Baker, undated, 1 l/2pp. Berkeley. (Folder 1)
- ALS (to Dorothy) April 11, 1944 (Folder 1)
- TLS, 1 p, Oct 23, 1947. Berkeley. From Deedie (Lydia Park). (Folder 1)
- TL, 1/2 pp retained or unsent or draft of letter to Park from Dorothy Baker about her projected novel. (Folder 1)
- Nov 8, 1947. 9 negatives sent to the Bakers. (Folder 1)
- TLS to the Bakers, Aug 1, 1951, Berkeley. (Folder 1)
- APC, Oct 19, 1951 (Folder 1)
- APC, Oct 25, 1951 (Folder 1)
- TLS, undated (Thursday) to Dorothy Baker from David Park who signs with a typed x and a small ink profolder drawing. (Folder 1)
- TLS to the Bakers, July 30, 1952 from Mrs. Park (Deedie). 2pp. (Folder 1)
- Undated TLS (in type with a d & a squiggle drawing) 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Undated TLS, 1p. To Bertrand & Mildred Bronson with holograph addenda, signed in type (d) with squiggle drawing. The Bronson/Baker/Park friendship alliance was very strong. (Folder 1)
- Undated, unsigned AL in pencil from Park to Dorothy Baker. (Folder 1)
- ALS, 3 pp, to Dorothy Baker ("dearly beloved") signed "D." With list of jazz songs, holograph, 1p. This would be a very early letter. (Folder 1)
- Undated TLS (Deedie) from Mrs Park (page one missing), early about Diebenkom, Park, painting etc. Early. (Folder 1)
- 4 pp (last page missing ?) to the Bakers, Berkeley, Aug 21. Pencil. (Folder 1)
- AL to Howard, with Park (?) pencil to line note, from Mildred Bronson, 2pp undated. (Folder 1)
- TLS 1 p, from David Park, undated (The Sabbath) (Folder 1)
- TLS from Mrs. Park, Jan 18, 1957 to the Bakers. (Folder 1)
- ALS, 4 pp from Deedie Park (?). Aug 3, 1953. Berekeley. (Folder 1)
- ALS, 2 pp from Deedie Park to Dorothy Baker, Jan 31. Her response to Baker's novel CASSANDRA (etc). (Folder 1)
- Series 2: Printed matter and Parkiana
- SF Art Association Bulletin Bulletin 12:8 (August 1946). Early Park exhibition announced. (Folder 2)
- 7 negatives of Park paintings (Dorothy Baker possession) (Folder 2)
- Engraved announcement, marriage of Park's daughter. (Folder 2)
- Whitney Museum of American Art TLS (1988) to Baker (Folder 2)
- two 1989 TLS to Baker & retained copy (Xerox) long TLS to Richard Armstrong at Whitney from Howard Baker, 1989. (Folder 2)
- 2 TLS from Henger about Park retrospective, to the Bakers. (Folder 2)
- Series 3: "David Park": Memoir by Howard Baker
- Original heavily corrected typescript, 3 1/2 pp. (Folder 3)
- Three page memoir, TS (Xeroxed). (Folder 3)
- Park exhibition catalogue, Salander-O'Reilly Galleries, NYC (1987) (Folder 3)